Hi, I am Rick Ivnik. I am the
Director of Biomedical Engineering
at the St. Louis VA Healthcare
System. I am here today to talk to
you about biomedical engineering
for informaticists.
The purpose of this presentation is
to provide you with a basic
understanding of the roles,
responsibilities, and functions of
Biomedical Engineering in the VA
and how the relationship with
Biomedical Engineering and
Informatics is extremely important
to the future of healthcare.
The learning objectives are
primarily to identify the roles,
responsibilities, and functions of
Biomedical Engineering in the VA,
to understand the healthcare
technologies that Biomedical
Engineering manages, and to define
the relationship between Biomedical
Engineering and Informatics. This
hopefully will lead you to be able
to recognize opportunities to be
able to work collaboratively
between Biomedical Engineering and
Informatics.
Our core function in Biomedical
Engineering, simply put, is to
provide support to advance patient
care by applying engineering,
technical, and managerial skills to
healthcare technologies.
The fundamental theorem we are
going to discuss is that in
biomedical informatics, the person
and the technology are greater than
the person alone. Essentially, if
we can offer the person a resource
that is something the person does
not already know, they can provide
better care to the patient.
This diagram describes the
relationships that are required for
this theorem to hold. Essentially,
when you have a patient, you have
two interactions with that patient.
The patient interacts with the
medical technology and the clinical
staff, both of which gather data
from the patient. That data is then
stored in another system. In order
for these relationships to work
correctly, Biomedical Engineering,
OIT (Office of Information &
Technology), and Informatics must
work as one.
Now, the reason biomedical
engineering and informaticists can
work so closely together is we have
some very similar characteristics.
For example, Informatics is a
data-driven organization. They love
data. It is what they work with.
Biomedical Engineering is very
analytical. We enjoy looking at the
data and doing analysis.
Informatics, you can give them a
problem, and they will be able to
diagnose it. If you give engineers
a problem, we will attempt to solve
it. Informatics understands process
and workflow. We understand
computers and technical systems.
Informaticists are able to see the
connections and clinical impacts
that technology can provide.
Biomedical Engineering, we are able
to visualize complex processes and
the interactions with other systems
for those equipment. Informaticists
are curious. Engineers are curious.
Informaticists have the ability to
communicate and translate with the
clinical staff, and biomedical
engineers have the ability to
communicate and create diagrams of
process flows on the administrative
side of the house. Informatics does
change management, and Biomedical
Engineering does project management.
In a recent survey of Informatics
staff across the VA, one of the
most surprising things we found out
is they want to work with
Biomedical Engineering. Eighty-five
percent of Informatics staff across
the VA identified that they want to
share experiences and have closer
integration with Biomedical
Engineering as a priority goal.